Very good. And now we're starting. All right, today's דף, daf, we're
on מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin דף daf י"ט. yud tet. We're a
little behind. We're basically in the middle of י"ח עמוד ב'. yud
chet amud bet.
We're right up to יתמא דאין עושין כיוצא בה. Yitama d'ein osin
k'yotze bah. It's really pretty much smack in the middle.
There's no good reference as to
where. We're תוספות וכי
תימא.
Tosfot v'chi
teima. We're a few lines up from that.
וכי תימא, v'chi teima, oh I see it's above that.
Yes. And then go a few lines up from that in the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, דאין, d'ein, the first line, first word on
the line is דאין. d'ein. We're
a few lines below that?
Above. דאין עושה, d'ein ose, דאין עושה כיוצא בה,
d'ein ose
k'yotze bah, like four or five lines above that.
וכי תימא v'chi teima that I see is above that.
No, וכי תימא, v'chi teima, we're in the lines of the גמרא,
Gemara, a few lines above the תוספות וכי תימא. Tosfot v'chi teima.
Oh, תוספות. Tosfot. Yeah, תוספות וכי תימא.
Tosfot v'chi teima. Sorry, sorry, sorry. דאין עושה. d'ein ose. Yeah, דאין
עושה כיוצא בה. d'ein ose k'yotze bah.
Everyone have it?
Here's where it is.
Joel, do you have it? Yeah? You have it. Okay. Rabbi, do
you have it now? I have it. You're good? Okay, fine. Okay,
anyway, so just a thirty-second review as to what we were trying
to prove. We were trying to remember we had the premise that
משקין mashkin cannot be מטמא metame משקין, mashkin, right? So משקין mashkin
not מטמא metame משקין, mashkin, משקין mashkin and אוכלין ochlin not מטמא
metame אוכלין, ochlin, but משקין mashkin can be מטמא metame אוכלין ochlin
and vice versa. But we said that it doesn't extend to
כלים, kelim, right? And
you know, one we had a couple ways of getting into that,
you know, we had the whole bunch of קל וחומר kal va'chomers
and we had the application of the principle דיו dyo last time,
if you remember, that was on top. And we also said that
basically that we're מטמא metame like one of
the other יתמא yitamas mentions it twice in that פסוק pasuk is
to מטמא metame המשקין hamashkin because it's because they're like predisposed to
מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, right? And we said that it can't be
a כלי, kli, it's a
משקין. mashkin. And we talked about its predisposition and then how that
works its way into אוכלין ochlin and the whole reason why אוכלין
ochlin become טמא tame is not so much because of אוכלין ochlin
and אוכלין, ochlin, but really because of משקין, mashkin, because משקין mashkin
are מכשיר makhshir other things. And whereas they themselves, in order to
become טמא tame don't need, you know, a הכשר, hekhsher, they're what
they are. So that's anyway, so יתמא דאין עושין כיוצא בה.
Yitama d'ein osin
k'yotze bah. So does not like does not create like in terms
of טומאה. tumah. So משקין mashkin would not be מטמא metame משקין.
mashkin. So the גמרא Gemara questions him. מהכא נפקא? Mehakha nafka? Is
that where we get it from? For this whole יתמא, yitama, this
double יתמא? yitama? I thought מהתם נפקא. Mehatam nafka. I thought we
have a different source for this. וכי יותן מים על זרע, V'chi
yutan mayim al zera, another this is this is for the classic
way of seeing this is הכשר זרעים, hekhsher zeraim, right? So if
this, let's say you have some sort of produce and then again,
the way food becomes prepared for טומאה tumah is that water falls
on it. And you know, you have to be relatively copacetic with
this water falling on it and then now it's in a state
of being ready to מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah such that let's say
if a dead שרץ sheretz fell on it, it can become טמא.
tame.
So וכי יותן מים על זרע, V'chi yutan mayim al zera, so
if it had been watered, ונפל מנבלתם עליו, v'nafal mivlatam alav, and
then and this שרץ sheretz falls on it, טמא הוא. tame hu.
So it says טמא, tame, it could have just said טמא, tame,
but it says טמא הוא. tame hu. So הוא טמא ואין עושה
טומאה כיוצא בה. hu tame v'ein ose tumah k'yotze bah. So he
darshens that from there, that it is טמא tame and it does
not create a טומאה tumah of a like way.
So what becomes טמא tame in that case?
I'm sorry? So what becomes טמא? tame?
מים. mayim. What does מים mayim fall on?
מים mayim falls on some, you know, produce, seeds, whatever, you know,
wheat, kernels of wheat. Okay. So that means the seed is going
to become טמא, tame, but אין עושה טומאה כיוצא בה. ein ose
tumah k'yotze bah. So it can't make another thing like it טמא.
tame. Like it would mean like another food. So the seed, the
seeds, I mean, let's say this seed touches a fruit. It can't
make another fruit טמא. tame. Right. It can't make another fruit טמא.
tame. It can make a משקין mashkin טמא, tame, right? We said
אוכלין ochlin can מטמא metame משקין, mashkin, and משקין mashkin מטמא metame
אוכלין, ochlin, but not but אוכלין ochlin cannot be מטמא metame אוכלין
ochlin and משקין mashkin cannot be מטמא metame משקין mashkin דאורייתא de-Oraita
anyway.
So just that one seed, if it's in a barrel of seeds,
oh, that's that
we'll get to that.
Forget hold that thought.
That's like the
but let's say it's not in a barrel, right? Let's say it's
on the table, and let's say there's no barrel. Then, you know,
then this other one touches it, it won't become טמא. tame. It
won't become another seed.
It will not. It would be kind of boring. So how are
people supposed to know which one?
That was the תרומה Terumah problem. The תרומה Terumah got mixed, טמא
תרומה, tame Terumah, טהור תרומה.
tahor Terumah. Well, presumably if it's like your field and, you know,
let's say you wanted to, you know, and you're watering your garden,
you don't know exactly. Right. Well, you don't know
exactly on a hot sunny day it dries up so fast.
Right. Right, you
might not be sure which one the שרץ Sheretz *Sheretz* fell on,
so a שרץ sheretz *Sheretz*, a dead שרץ sheretz *Sheretz*. Right, well
that's true, if
you don't know, okay, right, that's true, right. But then you just
deal with principles of like רוב *Rov* and ביטול *Bitul* and stuff
like that, you know.
So it gets very complicated.
Anyway, the point being though that we just say הוא *Hu* is
generally one of these limiting phrases and here we're taking it to
mean, at least we're דרש *Darsh*-ing it to mean that it can't
make a like, right? So we already have a source for like.
Why do we need this פסוק pasuk. *Passuk* now? Why do we
need this יטמא יטמא yitamei yitamei *Yitma Yitamei* that whole thing? It
mentions it twice, you know. We don't need that to tell us
that אין עושה טומאה כיוצא בה tumah keyotzei bah, *Ein Oseh Tumah
Kayotze Bah* because we can דרש *Darsh* it from someplace else. And
you know,
as Rabbi Lerer was mentioning somewhat jokingly in passing before the דף
*Daf*, like you know, שרץ sheretz *Sheretz* by the way, it's not
like, you know, waiter, a dead fly in my soup. It's more
like waiter, I have a dead viper in my soup. And you
know,
or he says, oh, would you rather the porcupine? You know what
I mean? Like, you know, that's what the שרצים *Sheratzim* are. It's
not like a bee or a fly. It's something a little bigger,
like lizards, you know,
vipers and stuff like that. No, but just so you know.
So, if other cultures at that time had these kind of taboo
things, you know, things that you can't eat?
That's a good question. I really don't know.
Are we the only ones that obsessed on them?
I don't know. But didn't your son take a course like that
or something? Did your son take a course like that, you know,
comparative, you know, like I
remember him wondering if other cultures had this kind of system of
purity and impurity. With women they certainly did, yes. But with food?
Yeah, I don't know. Very good question. I really don't know.
Anyway, so our point now is that you know, we took פסוקים
pesukim. *Pesukim* with water, right? Because that יטמא יטמא yitamei yitamei, *Yitma
Yitamei* was, you know, that one was also dealing with a water
kind of case. I mean, there's food and water, but part of
it was with water. And now we have this other case of
water with
זרע *Zera*. And from both of them we're learning that אין עושה
טומאה Tumah כיוצא בה *Ein Oseh Tumah Kayotze Bah*, that it cannot
create a טמא Tamei. *Tamei* object of its own nature, is basically
a way of saying this. So why do we need both? That's
basically the question. So the answer is חד משקין mashkin הבאים מחמת
שרץ sheretz *Chad Mashkin HaBaim Mechamat Sheretz*. So one is talking about
a משקה mashkeh *Mashke*, משקין mashkin *Mashkin*, you know, something liquid that
became טמא tamei *Tamei* because of a שרץ sheretz *Sheretz*. And which
is probably the one we just cited. והחד משקין mashkin הבאים מחמת
כלי kli, *VeChad Mashkin HaBaim Mechamat Kli*.
And the other is that they became טמא tamei *Tamei* because of
the כלי kli. *Kli*. Now, again, the שרץ sheretz *Sheretz* went into
the כלי kli *Kli*, but the שרץ sheretz *Sheretz* didn't touch the
משקה mashkeh *Mashke* directly, right? The שרץ *Sheretz* touched the כלי kli
*Kli*, the כלי kli, *Kli* contained the משקה mashkeh, *Mashke*, and that's
how the משקה mashkeh *Mashke* became טמא tamei. *Tamei*. So and that
would be probably the יטמא יטמא yitamei yitamei *Yitma Yitamei*. Okay, and
then although they're both related to שרץ *Sheretz*, but one is coming
into contact more directly with the שרץ *Sheretz*, right?
So for this little piece the קושיא *Kushya* is מהכא נפקא מהתם
נפקא *MeHacha Nafka MeHatam Nafka*, right? And then there's a second פסוק
pasuk *Passuk* and now the resolution is
they're talking about two different cases slightly.
One is the הלכתי *Halachic* outcome is the
same, each פסוק pasuk *Passuk* treats a different case with the same
outcome.
Right, case one would be the שרץ *Sheretz* touches the משקה mashkeh
*Mashke* directly, case two is that the שרץ *Sheretz* touches the כלי
kli *Kli* which is containing the משקה mashkeh. *Mashke*, and now the
משקה *Mashke* becomes טמא tamei *Tamei* vis-a-vis the כלי kli
*Kli*. Okay, but one is more direct, right? One is שרץ *Sheretz*
touches the משקה *Mashke* itself.
Okay, and it's easier if you see a שרץ *Sheretz* touching the
barrel or whatever, it's more visible than if it just gets in
the water, if you just, you know, it's a much smaller area
that's contained, at least you know it was, it's much clearer of
a case.
Okay, וצריכין *VeTzrichin*, even though we would need still
both of these verses. דאי אשמעינן במשקין הבאים מחמת כלי kli. *De'i
Ashmian BeMashkin HaBaim Mechamat Kli*, so talk about the, you know, the
more indirect case so to speak. So in that case, דאי אשמעינן
במשקין הבאים מחמת כלי kli. משום דלא חמירי *De'i Ashmian BeMashkin HaBaim
Mechamat Kli Mishum DeLo Chamiri*, you would have thought that it
just applies to that because because again, on the one hand you'd
say it's more of a bigger חידוש chiddush *Chidush* for it to
become טמא tamei. *Tamei*, but on the other hand the טומאה Tumah
*Tumah* won't go as far, right? Because you know, every time like
a ראשון rishon, *Rishon* can make a שני sheni. *Sheni*, שלישי shlishi
*Shlishi*, but a שני sheni, *Sheni*, you know, in other words it
can't make as many levels afterwards.
So basically, so the משקין mashkin *Mashkin* again, because the way it
worked was this שרץ *Sheretz* touched the כלי kli. *Kli* which touched
the משקה *Mashke*. So now this משקה *Mashke* is now a שני
sheni, *Sheni*. So you may say okay, it's a שני sheni, *Sheni*,
so you know שרץ *Sheretz* is a very, you know, so it's
not, it won't, it'll make it טמא tamei. *Tamei* because the טומאה
Tumah *Tumah* that it'll have won't go further much further, right? Because
I know there's a unless you're רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But basically
if we're talking about חולין Chullin stuff, it stops there, right? It
won't become it won't make anything else טמא. tamei It doesn't have
as strong a טומאה Tumah on it. So therefore you may say
okay, בר משקה דבאי מחמת שרץ, Bar mashkeh d'vaei machmat sheretz, דחמירי,
d'chamiri,
right?
Because it can now מטמא metamei other things, אימא עושה טומאה כיוצא
בה. eima oseh tumah kayotze bah. I might have said that actually
it can create something טמא tamei like itself.
Like foods, because it's more direct, so it's more powerful.
More טומאה Tumah power. Right. Exactly. Right. So you might have said
that it can create like, in that case, when
שרץ directly touches it.
So and the whole thing means that in some
way טומאה Tumah affects טומאה tumah, and the identity of the object
are related. Right? In other words, טומאה tumah, doesn't transfer from like
to like. Right. So there is some underlying idea here that has
to do with the relationship between טומאה tumah and the identity of
something. Just wanted to put that out there right now.
Right, and and not to complicate this further, but all this is
מדאורייתא mid'oraita by the way, מדרבנן mid'rabbanan we would say that it
does but we're talking about darshaning the פסוקים. pesukim Okay, fine. So
now we're saying that okay,
it's a bigger חידוש to tell you you know טומאה מחמת שרץ
tumah machmat sheretz that even then, which is a power more powerful
טומאה, tumah still like does not create like. Okay, so then השמעינן
משקה דבאי מחמת שרץ, hashmieinan mashkeh d'vaei machmat sheretz, וכל שכן משקה
דבאי מחמת כלי. v'chol shekein mashkeh d'vaei machmat kli. So
say the second case, right? If even in a case of a
more powerful טומאה, tumah. still like can't create like, certainly
in a case that it's more indirect that like can't create like.
So although you know we're very it's an interesting answer, although we're
very into darshaning all these יתרים yitayrim and יטמא yitma יטמא yitamei?
and קל וחומרס kal v'chomers and דייוס, dayos, now we're saying מילתא
דאתיא בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא, milta d'atya b'kal v'chomer tarach
v'chtav lah kra,
which is another way of saying אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
but nevertheless sometimes the תורה Torah wants to go through the trouble
of telling you something you may have been able to figure out
on your own. And you know, maybe speaking to what we were
saying before, this is all so complicated, you know, sometimes it's just
good to spell things out. So yes, maybe we could have figured
it out but better to have it explicit.
Well, it's
hardly
it's hardly explicit,
it takes a whole construct here around it. But it's really interesting
this tension between learning a דין din על פי סברא al pi
svara and learning it על פי המקרא. al pi hamikra.
And here the גמרא'ס Gemara's taking the opportunity to say
if I can do it with פסוקים pesukim I would rather do
it with פסוקים than just rely on human creativity.
Well you know there's this tension that at least in areas of
טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, but you know there's this tension over there,
we've seen in other גמרות Gemaros about which is the greater מידה
middah like עוקר הרים oker harim or סיני, Sinai, right?
It's a very very important tension, really important, and it's great that
you but you know, but thank you for pointing that out. But
I would say though that again, like maybe in areas of טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'taharah which are more abstruse, it's better to have a
פסוק. pasuk That could be the counterpoint to that. Okay, אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי, amar leih Ravina l'Rav Ashi, והא אמר רבא veha
amar Rava getting back to what we mentioned yesterday, לא רבי יוסי
סבר כרבי עקיבא ולא רבי עקיבא סבר כרבי יוסי. lo Rabbi Yosei
savar k'Rabbi Akiva v'lo Rabbi Akiva savar k'Rabbi Yosei. Remember that? That
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei remember there were a couple of opinions as
to how far this goes. Remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says not
at all, right? And then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says entirely, in
terms of you know how far you take these טומאות, tumot, you
know whether טומאת משקין tumat mashkin is מדאורייתא mid'oraita or not and
you know all that. So remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no
and then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah took it to a stronger level,
then we had הדר ביה hadar beih and then we said well
how much was he חוזר, chozer, was he חוזר chozer entirely like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or just כלים? keilim? And then and then
you had the opinions of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and you also
had a colleague but right now we're focusing on רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosei,
sort of split your vote, right? אוכלין ochlin yes, כלים keilim no.
So and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei cited you know רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei cited an opinion about יטמא yitma יטמא, yitma right? And we
said that he cited in the name of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva,
But
we
had the same that really neither holds like the other. It's sort
of like you know using someone's methodology but you don't necessarily agree
with the conclusion. So didn't רבא Rava say לא רבי יוסי סבר
כרבי עקיבא ולא רבי עקיבא סבר כרבי יוסי? lo Rabbi Yosei savar
k'Rabbi Akiva v'lo Rabbi Akiva savar k'Rabbi Yosei? So
one did not hold like the other and we're going to explain
we're going to get into that. So
basically, you know what, let's let's let's see. So one second, so
basically, so the point then is though that
take
the other case of of our כלי, kli. right? Which had the
שרץ fall into it which is now מטמא metamei the משקה which
is now a שני. sheni,
So but the point but it would seem like that you
can have a שלישי shlishi. in the case of חולין, chullin, like
can't be מטמא metamei like but it can מטמא metamei something else,
right? So in other words if we're trying to say oh. It
becomes a טומאה tumah כיוצא בה, right? It can, so let's say
it was טומאה שלא כיוצא בה, tumah shelo keyotzei bah, like a
משקה to an אוכל, ochel, and then it could create another level.
Do you got that? Our case was a שני, sheni. remember? I'll
say it one more time. The שרץ fell into the, it
touched the side of the כלי. kli The כלי kli, is containing
the משקה, right? So the שרץ is an אב, av, the כלי
kli is a ראשון, rishon. the משקה in there is a שני,
sheni right? And we said, okay fine, a משקה cannot create another,
cannot create טומאה tumah? in another משקה. The implication is it can
create טומאה tumah in an אוכל, ochel, which would be a שלישי.
shlishi But the problem is that's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva where יוסי
Yossi does not hold like that. And now we're just and now
we're just so how
that lines up now.
So how does that work? Is is basically our question. But we're
going to get into it in just a second.
It's the third generation, רב אשי Rav Ashi and רב כהנא Rav
Kahana who are the later generation discussing what רבא Rava the middle
said about two of the first generation. So you have here three
generations, the opinions of three generations. The third is trying to figure
out what the other and who agreed with who.
Right. Yeah.
You want to say something? רב אשי Rav Ashi of the later.
Well, you you see the רש"י, Rashi, you see the you see
on there's a מסורת הש"ס Masoret Hashas right underneath that there's a
רש"י Rashi והא
אמר רבא לא רבי
יוסי.
ve-ha amar Rava lo Rabbi
Yossi.
Yeah, we're going to get up to it, we're going to read
it right now here.
Okay good. Because I don't know what that. Yeah.
So, anyway the point the point is that you know they don't
hold like the other and it would seem almost inescapable that he
would hold that a that there is a שלישי בחולין, shlishi be-chullin,
which is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva opinion but not רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yossi. So how do we get to that? How do we reconcile
that base of the? Anyway, we're going to see it. אמר ליה
רב אשי לרב כהנא. Amar lei Rav Ashi le-Rav Kahana. So we're
going to explore as to why one does not hold like the
other. We said again, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. did not hold like
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi did not hold like
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva, So now now we're going to have a
statement and we're going to then unpack it a little bit. Okay,
so אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא בשלמא רבי יוסי סבר לה
כרבי עקיבא, Amar lei Rav Ashi le-Rav Kahana bishlama Rabbi Yossi savar
lah ke-Rabbi Akiva, I understand רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi does not hold
like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva דתניא, de-tanya, אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi
Yossi, we've this is his teaching, מניין לרביעי בקודש שהוא פסול. minayin
li-revii ba-kodesh she-hu pasul.
Everyone agrees that רביעי בקודש revii ba-kodesh is פסול. pasul. Remember like,
you know, חולין chullin goes as far as a שני, sheni then
תרומה terumah goes I mean generally forget about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
for the moment, but then תרומה terumah goes up until a שלישי
shlishi and then קודש kodesh goes up until a רביעי, revii, right?
So everyone agrees that the that a רביעי בקודש revii ba-kodesh is
פסול. pasul. ודין
הוא,
ve-din
hu, and that actually makes sense. ומה מחוסר כיפורים. u-mah mechusar kippurim.
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is a different case. So let's say
for instance like the getting back to the יולדת, yoledet, right? So
she, you know, she טבל-ed tovel and all that, but she has
to wait a certain number of days right now. There yeah, right,
there's being טהור, tahor, right, in terms of eating תרומה terumah let's
say, but then there's another thing about actually being able to partake
of קודש, kodesh, which which you can't do until you bring your
קרבן, korban, because right she has to bring her קרבן korban after
a certain number of days depending whether it's. So she's it's almost
like
her time is up but she until the next morning
she can't but it's not even the next morning, but then she
has to bring her קרבן korban like her her her קינין, kinin,
right? So it's viewed until she brings her קרבן, korban, it's almost
like a long טבול יום. tvul yom. That's the way it's conceptualized.
So so
this is the מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kippurim. You didn't bring your כיפורים,
kippurim, your כפרה, kapparah, your קרבן. korban. So so
in that kind of a case, you may it's not necessarily just
a woman, I mean like it can be anybody, but that's an
example we. Yeah, I had that case. Yeah. So so someone like
that, שמותר בתרומה, she-mutar be-terumah, you can eat תרומה, terumah, you just
can't eat קודש. kodesh. So פסול
בקודש. pasul ba-kodesh. Then שלישי שפסול בתרומה. shlishi she-pasul be-terumah. We also
know that remember we said a תרומה terumah can go up until
a שלישי. shlishi. So a שלישי שפסול בתרומה shlishi she-pasul be-terumah אינו
דין שיעשה רביעי בקודש. eino din she-yaaseh revii ba-kodesh.
So and then he's going to some רש"י Rashi for a second.
ולמדנו שלישי בקודש מן התורה ורביעי מקל וחומר. ve-lamadnu shlishi ba-kodesh min
ha-Torah ve-revii mi-kal va-chomer. So what emerges from this is we learned
and we're going to cite what our פסוק pasuk is, that שלישי
בקודש shlishi ba-kodesh is מן התורה. min ha-Torah. And then the רביעי
revii is a קל וחומר kal va-chomer from what we just said
from מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim and then תרומה. terumah.
So the שלישי shlishi and and I'll circle back in a second.
שלישי מן התורה. shlishi min ha-Torah. So שלישי בקודש. shlishi ba-kodesh. He's
saying we take for granted from a פסוק pasuk that a שלישי
בקודש shlishi ba-kodesh is פסול מן התורה. pasul min ha-Torah. How? שלישי
מן התורה דכתיב והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל. shlishi min
ha-Torah dikhtiv ve-ha-basar asher yiga be-khol tamei lo ye-akhel. So any this
is this is talking about קודש kodesh that touches כל
טמא, khol tamei, then לא יאכל. lo ye-akhel. So if this meat,
בשר קודש basar kodesh touches anything that's טמא tamei. it can't be
eaten. So מי לא עסקינן דנגע בשני. mi lo askinan di-nega be-sheni.
So are we not talking about a case that this שני, sheni,
this meat touches touches a שני. sheni So that means that if
the meat touches if the meat if this שני sheni touches the
קודש, kodesh, that's now the קודש kodesh now becomes a שלישי, shlishi,
right? Every time it touches something else it's a level removed.
So basically the point is that a שני sheni is called טמא.
tamei Because otherwise because otherwise
it wouldn't. Just said let's say, you know, would have said שני
גבי שרץ sheni gabai sheretz or something like that if it were
an אב. av. So and our whole point was, you had, remember
our יטמא yitma. יטמא? So let the and in the case of
the in the case of the שרץ falling into the vessel having
the liquid and that's called יטמא and we said יטמא is it
makes other things מטמא. metamei. So it's called טמא tamei, basically. So
the point is that in the world of in the world of
משקין mashkin, in a כלי, kli, that משקין mashkin, was a שני,
sheni, right? And it still says that פסוק pasuk, of יטמא. So
it's called טמא. tamei. So now if let's say so we see
now שני sheni are called טמא. tamei. So and then we have
this פסוק pasuk that הבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל. habasar
asher yigah bechol tamei lo yeachel. So the טמא tamei? is a
שני sheni and now this שני sheni touches בשר קודש. basar kodesh.
בשר קודש basar kodesh is now a שלישי shlishi and the תורה
Torah is telling you מן התורה min ha-Torah that you can't eat
it. So so now we see that a שלישי shlishi is מן
התורה. min ha-Torah. So what he's saying is we can figure out
רביעי revii מקל וחומר mikal vachomer because we know also that a
שלישי shlishi is פסול pasul בתרומה. betrumah. And קדשים kodshim are more
חמור chamor than תרומה terumah and and קדשים kodshim go get are,
you know, we have an explicit פסוק pasuk. telling you that you
even have a שלישי shlishi by קדשים, kodshim, then certainly we can
figure that there should also be רביעי revii מקל וחומר. mikal vachomer.
That's basically what he's saying. So fine,
אי סלקא דעתך ei salka daitzach סבר רבי עקיבא savar Rabbi Akiva
נתני נמי רביעי בתרומה וחמישי בקודש. niteni nami revii betrumah ve-chamishi be-kodesh.
So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi only is only talking about a רביעי
בקודש revii be-kodesh and a שלישי בתרומה. shlishi be-terumah. But if again
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva takes everything a step further, right? Because remember
that a שני, sheni it can only go you only get up
to a שני sheni in חולין. chullin. Then a שלישי, shlishi, this
is the common between. A שלישי shlishi in תרומה terumah and a
רביעי revii in קדשים. kodshim. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, says everything
goes down one more level because he says you can get up
to a שלישי בחולין, shlishi be-chullin, which means you should get up
to רביעי בתרומה revii be-terumah and a חמישי בקודש. chamishi be-kodesh. But
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is not saying that. He's stopping at a
fourth in קדשים. kodshim. So that's the point basically. So so that's
how we know that, you know, those two opinions are not like
each other. So that's how we know רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi does
not hold like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva because he would have taken
it further is basically what we're saying from. So ורבי עקיבא לא
סבר כרבי יוסי מנלן? ve-Rabbi Akiva lo savar ke-Rabbi Yossi menalan? So
okay, how do we know the reverse? That רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
does not hold like
רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? אמר ליה דלא לישתמיט תנא וליתני רביעי בתרומה
וחמישי בקודש. amar lei dela lishtamit tana ve-lisni revii be-terumah ve-chamishi be-kodesh.
So so the point over here is
if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, would actually hold like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi and talk about all these קל וחומרים, kal vachomerim, because we
just said a second ago רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi had these קל
וחומרים. kal vachomerim. So in the basis of these קל וחומרים, kal
vachomerim, can it possibly be, now remember רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva you
know, was the one that says it makes up until a שלישי
בחולין, shlishi be-chullin. right? But he didn't say how far it goes
with תרומה terumah and קדשים kodshim actually. We're assuming that, you know,
that based on what he'd said, we should take it further. But
he actually didn't say that it goes further. He just said that,
you know, you get up to a שלישי בחולין. shlishi be-chullin, So
if, but so basically the point being that if really somebody held
like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, and namely רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, who's
doing all these דרשות drashot a second ago, then would it be
that no other תנא tana would ever come from somewhere and teach
this exactly that that you can make it you can have a
רביעי בתרומה revii be-terumah and a חמישי בקודש chamishi be-kodesh and say
that בשם רבי עקיבא היא, be-shem Rabbi Akiva hi, right? So if
everyone held the basis of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva. you just take
everything a step further, then why don't we have any explicit teaching
anywhere that says you actually get further
in, you would get a רביעי בתרומה revii be-terumah and a חמישי
בקודש. chamishi be-kodesh.
That small detail question? Yes.
למדנו שלישי בקודש מן התורה ורביעי מקל וחומר. lamadnu shlishi be-kodesh min
ha-Torah ve-revii mikal vachomer. Right. That means that שלישי בקודש shlishi be-kodesh
is מן התורה min
ha-Torah and then if that קודש kodesh touches something else, it'll
make it a רביעי דרבנן? revii de-rabbanan?
No,
he's trying to say it should be מן התורה. min ha-Torah.
מן התורה? min ha-Torah? In other words,
just because it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer doesn't automatically make it
a דרבנן de-rabbanan in this case?
Correct, correct. What he means מן התורה min ha-Torah means you have
explicit פסוק, pasuk. right? But we still figure out מן התורה min
ha-Torah should be טמא tamei from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
Yeah, exactly. That's really interesting too. In other words, the פסוק is
the foundation for this entire transference of טומאה. tumah? Correct. You learn
potentially from שלישי shlishi to רביעי revii from a logical deduction. Right.
But still a deduction that's coming from the implications of the פסוק.
Correct. Phenomenal.
Correct. So
the, but okay, and again, because of that, we know then we
held that since he didn't take it any further, he's not holding
like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not
holding and then vice versa. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, is not holding
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi because רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva although he
mentioned that you get up to a שלישי בחולין, shlishi be-chullin, but
no one actually and although רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva takes חולין chullin
level one more because again we only really מן התורה min ha-Torah
only have up until a שני בחולין, sheni be-chullin, right? But רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, even a שלישי shlishi בחולין, be-chullin, which
then implies that everything else goes down one more
level and תרומה terumah should be רביעי revii and קדשים kodshim should
be
a חמישי. chamishi. So you know meaning if you'd have that קל
וחומר kal vachomer just like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said oh you
have a קל וחומר kal vachomer then somebody should have said oh
guess what we have a קל וחומר kal vachomer and we know
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says take this קל וחומר kal vachomer
and say that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would hold that you go
further but you don't have that.
So therefore
it's not you know רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. wouldn't hold of this
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And so but what's interesting is now again
this whole point remember רבינא Ravina and רב אשי Rav Ashi as
you were mentioning we're trying to figure this all out you know
who holds what back in the prior generations. So now the question
is you know again all fine and good that you don't have
a proof
that no one came out and said it but so does that
mean that the absence of a teaching is a positive that no
one holds like him right? You know can you infer that from
a non-teaching that it's rejected? Can you do that? So ואנן הכי
ניקום ונסמוך? v'anan hachi nekum v'nismach? So is absence of evidence evidence
essentially? That's the question. You get that?
ואנן הכי ניקום ונסמוך. v'anan hachi nekum v'nismach.
That's where I am.
Just smack in the middle of the line one two three four
five six seven lines down.
Line begins with ה. he. A line above where it says חגיגה
כף Chagigah chaf on the right. Right. So ואנן הכי ניקום ונסמוך
v'anan hachi nekum v'nismach right? We're trying to prove because there's no
teaching that it's rejected right? So the point is is absence of
evidence evidence because you don't have a teaching that means it's rejected
which means you don't have a teaching. So נפק nafak you get
that? What
if
they made up their own mind then? If they didn't have a
tradition then what would they decide?
Right now we're talking about they didn't
live in the time of.
No
I mean there's going to be you speak to what you said
it's going to be the next two lines. Okay. So נפק רב
אשי nafak Rav Ashi so do we have a teaching or do
we not? So let's make up our minds right. So נפק nafak
you know can we infer or not. נפק רב אשי ואי תימא
רב כהנא דק ואשכח. nafak Rav Ashi v'isayma Rav Kahana dak v'ashkach.
So okay רב אשי Rav Ashi
who just said a second ago you know is absence of evidence
evidence? So maybe he or maybe רב כהנא Rav Kahana went out
דק dak you know investigated like בדיקה bedika ואשכח v'ashkach and he
found actually a teaching. הכי תנן הכלי מצרף את מה שבתוכו לקודש
אבל לא לתרומה. hachi tnan hakli m'tzaref es mah she-besocho l'kodesh aval
lo l'serumah. So let's say it's all together in a barrel.
Remember the case our case was one touched the other but not
in a barrel but דק ואשכח הכי תנן הכלי מצרף את מה
שבתוכו
לקודש אבל לא לתרומה.
dak v'ashkach hachi tnan hakli m'tzaref es mah she-besocho l'kodesh
aval lo l'serumah. So let's say it's all in a bowl barrel
whatever. So the כלי kli is מצרף m'tzaref what's in it for
קודש kodesh אבל לא לתרומה aval lo l'serumah
but not for תרומה terumah ורביעי
בקודש פסול
v'revi'i ba-kodesh
pasul and a רביעי בקודש revi'i b'kodesh. and a שלישי shlishi בתרומה.
bi-serumah. And and with that ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן מעידותו
של רבי עקיבא היא משנה
זו.
v'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan
me'iduso shel Rabbi Akiva hi mishna
zu. Actually let me just before we get too far let me
just explain what's going on over here. So the point being that
if you don't say that the reason why we said a רביעי
revi'i and a שלישי shlishi. and you need to say that and
combine that with the barrel is because think about it. So let's
say forget about grains for a minute let's say I have a
barrel of
apples right. And let's say they're
תרומה terumah right. And so they're all together in this bowl and
then let's say you know the שרץ touches the bowl and then
the bowl and and now these are in in the bowl that
was touched by the שרץ so they become a שני right. So
a שני can make a שלישי. shlishi So let's say they're in
forget the barrel case for a minute they're not in a barrel
this touches this so now this is the שני this is the
שלישי shlishi right. So we don't take it any further than that.
But what we do say is the whole barrel becomes טמא. tamei
So the point is that it's in the barrel. It's not because
one is touching another and the other's touching the other because then
you get into like a you get into a hundred right. Let's
say there are a hundred barrels there so you have one I
mean a hundred apples over there and they're all in a line
right. Here, here, here. So this touches this to make it a
שלישי shlishi. this touches that to make it a רביעי revi'i there's
another apple there to make it a חמישי chamishi you get it?
If you're just dealing because one is touching
another then אין לדבר סוף ein ladavar sof right you can get
up until a hundred if there are a hundred apples in a
line right then then it never ends. So the point being it's
not because one is touching another it's because the barrel is viewed
as a uniting overarching entity
that contains.
ואין לדבר סוף v'ein ladavar sof no you'd say that there's only
a
limited the טומאה tumah power gets depleted at a certain point. It's
sort of like a כלי ראשון kli rishon you know it's like
a כלי שני kli sheni on שבת. Shabbos. Right. There is I
hate to say it no such thing as a כלי שלישי. kli
shlishi. In other words everything is a כלי שני kli sheni once
it becomes a כלי שני kli sheni so to speak.
So so why can't it be that?
In other words, okay, it's a line, the apples are lined up.
You're the only one I know who'd give that example. That's a
good example, right? But at a certain point there's no more טומאה
*tumah*, it doesn't matter if it's the fifth, the sixth, the seventh,
the eighth, the twelfth apple. That's it. They're all חמישי chamishi לטומאה
*chamishi letumah*. Why can you argue with that?
Well, what we're trying to say is that right, no, but the
teaching is that the point is that it's through the כלי kli.
*kli*, it's not through the touching it. It's now... it's...
aha, okay. So it doesn't matter whether that is or is not
a perfect or imperfect
contrasting example. The point is about the power of the כלי kli
*kli* and its influence for the transference of טומאה *tumah*.
Right, and it's not because one's touching the
other, or some other hypothetical we might come up with. Okay, good.
So that's what we just learned.
So this saying, these guys of a later generation, the Talmud was
considering the possibility that we can't reconstruct the assumption that there was
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer, *kal vachomer* for an earlier תנא *tanna*
if that תנא *tanna* didn't have some source. That's what they're saying.
In other words, it's the later generation that's trying to understand what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva's* position was, and they're actually saying
at one point, if there wasn't an explicit
לימוד *limud*, we can't reconstruct his position potentially based only on the
fact that he might have thought a קל וחומר kal v'chomer *kal
vachomer* or not. Right. That's like unbelievable. Okay. And as
the Talmud would be shorthand as long
as it's bad.
So that was our teaching, כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו kli m'tzaref mah
she-b'tocho לקודש אבל לא לתרומה *kli metzaref ma shebetocho lekodesh aval lo
leterumah*, and you get as far as a רביעי בקודש revi'i b'kodesh,
*revi'i bakodesh* פסול *pasul* ושלישי בתרומה v'shlishi b'trumah. *ushlishi baterumah*.
ושלישי בתרומה *ushlishi baterumah*. ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן מעדותו של רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. נשנית משנה Mishnah
זו *Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan me'eduto shel Rabbi Akiva nishnit mishna zu*.
Where a שלישי shlishi, *shlishi* and a רביעי בקודש revi'i b'kodesh. *revi'i
bakodesh*, that that's more חמור *chamur* in other words. קודש *Kodesh* is
always more חמור *chamur*.
קודש *Kodesh* attracts טומאה
*tumah* another level,
be another level, whereas תרומה trumah *terumah* stops or תרומה *terumah* doesn't
have the capacity to become even more טמא tamei *tamei*
than
שלישי *shlishi*.
Correct. The more טומאה *tumah* something can attract, the more קודש *kodesh*
it is, the more respected it is.
Or the more קודש *kodesh* it can... the more קודש *kodesh* it
is, the more...
you're learning it from the obverse, right? In other words, the
קדשים kodshim, *kodshim* become the most טמא tamei *tamei* because it's the
most קודש *kodesh* and it's the most restrictive.
Right. Okay, good. ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן מעדותו של רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. נשנית משנה
זו *Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan me'eduto shel Rabbi
Akiva nishnit mishna zu*. So דתנן di-tnan,
*detnan*, it's actually a משנה *mishna*, not a תניא *tanya*, דתנן *detnan*.
This is a case of
a טבול יום tvul yom *tevul yom* that touches something
and again, like let's say, there
are in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* there are a
lot of things that you can touch clearly.
And there were a couple of things that were mentioned in that.
So we're going to read the משנה *mishna* עדיות Eduyot. *Eduyos*, I
wish I had it here, I should have brought it. It's not
quoted in its entirely, in its entirety either,
but let's see what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has over here if he
said... one second.
Okay anyway, so there's אוכלין ochlin *ochlin*. Anyway, so the point is,
let's say a טבול יום tvul yom *tevul yom* touches אוכלין *ochlin*
of קודש *kodesh*, touches like a קרבן *korban*, whatever, you know. Part
of a... a טבול יום *tevul yom* is somebody who
has,
you know, there's a מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim* and there's a טבול
יום *tevul yom*. He did not have what's known as הערב שמש
*ha'erev shemesh*. So the point is like the sun has
not set, he went to the מקוה *mikvah*, right? But but so
it's still a day of his מקוה *mikvah* and it's not the
next day yet.
Otherwise he went to the מקוה *mikvah* during the day and he's
got
to wait till sunset to become completely טהור tahor *tahor*. I mean,
to remove the טומאה *tumah*. Right. But he didn't bring the קרבן
*korban*. Right. So a טבול יום *tevul yom* is not completely טהור
tahor. *tahor* though he went to the מקוה *mikvah* because he didn't
have what's known as הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh*, it didn't become the
next day. So and he touches foods, whatever, whatever it is, a
case, you know, over there, touches some food, he can make them,
he can make them טמא tamei, *tamei*.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* added to that, not just
food items, but סולת *soles*, well, סולת *soles* is food, but קטורת
ketores. *ketores* is not food, לבונה *levonah* is not food, and גחלים
gechalim *gechalim* are certainly not food. גחלים *Gechalim* are the coals, right?
So you know, the coals that were used to burn the קטורת
*ketores*, for instance. So all that also, שאם נגע טבול יום במקצתם
פסל את כולם *she'im naga tevul yom bemiktzatam pasal es kulam*. So
all together. Yeah,
they're all together.
The person, the person who's the טבול יום *tevul yom* touches this
stuff? Yeah, the person who's a טבול יום *tevul yom*
touches this stuff.
How does He’s a point, I mean, you know, he touches the
מזבח mizbeach, which is like, you know, your כלי kli. that’s מצטרף
mitztaref all גחלים on it, right? So every one of them, although
you don’t let’s say, let’s say you know, he touches this coal,
all the rest of them
are
the apples lined up in a row.
That’s the apples lined up in a row, but this is, but
they’re in a כלי. kli. They’re in a כלי. That’s the difference.
They’re in the
כלי.
Okay, fine. It’s in its כלי. It’s in its container.
So I mean, let’s say there were apples lined up in a
row, you wouldn’t say that. But you would say that if the
טבול יום touches the, you know,
the טבול יום is
ראשון לטומאה.
rishon l'tumah. Mastowitch?
What exactly is he? Is he an אב? av?
No, he’s not an אב. av. He’s not an אב.
av. He’s gotta be ראשון לטומאה. rishon l'tumah.
I assume, right? Now is any human?
Yes, he would be a ראשון לטומאה rishon l'tumah because any, touches
the, he touches the,
he touches the
let’s say, let’s say if he touches the מזבח, mizbeach the מזבח
mizbeach would be a שני then everything else in there would be
a שלישי.
But things like if a person touches,
touches משקין mashkin, which is שלישי לטומאה, shlishi l'tumah,
the human being becomes רביעי לטומאה? revi'i l'tumah?
Well, משקין’s mashkin a little different. רבנן Rabbanan made a גזירה gezeira
that ידים yadayim are שניות לטומאה shniyot l'tumah and if I’m getting
this correct, רבנן Rabbanan made a גזירה gezeira that ידים yadayim are
שניות לטומאה shniyot l'tumah and not only that, if it then touches
משקין, mashkin upgrades it to ראשון.
So the human being, human being adds טומאה?
ידים. Yadayim. ידים Yadayim though. Like you know, I don’t want to
get into anything like inherently טמא tamei kind of thing, you know?
Right. I understand. Okay.
So anyway, the point being though because if you would say that,
that’s why it’s been said the apples lined up in a row.
If you would say that it was a case of apples lined
up in a row, then he’d be like potentially a חמישי or
whatever, right? Remember that? Like you know, the one, the other, the
other, the other. But the point is that it’s on the מזבח
which is a כלי that combines everything that’s in it.
And this is by non-foodstuff, right?
Anyway, so the point is that so רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva So
we, you know, this, remember we had a thing, "Oh, no one
said the name רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva anything?" Well, now someone does
say in the name of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So this is
an outcome of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva
But the point is he only got as far as a רביעי,
revi'i right? That was the point. We just had כלי מצרף מה
שבתוכו לקודש ולא לתרומה ורביעי בקודש פסול ושלישי בתרומה. kli m'tzaref mah
she-b'tocho l'kodesh v'lo l'trumah v'revi'i b'kodesh pasul v'shlishi b'trumah. This is, this
is a משנה of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in עדיות. ושלישי בתרומה.
ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן מעדותו של רבי עקיבא
נשנית משנה זו v'amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan me'eiduto
shel Rabbi Akiva nishnit Mishnah zo and only so you get up
to a רביעי, revi'i, right? So now getting back to what we
started with, if we had this whole קל וחומר, you would have
taken it further. That was the whole point, right? You would have
gone up to a שלישי,
I mean a רביעי בתרומה וחמישי בקודש. revi'i b'trumah v'chamishi b'kodesh. But
he doesn’t say that. He just says up until רביעי בקודש. revi'i
b'kodesh. So it must mean that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn’t hold
from that קל וחומר we’re saying up above in the beginning of
the page.
Did I lose everybody? What we’re trying again, you know, there’s a
lot of gyrations back and forth. We’re trying to say רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva does not hold like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei does not hold like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva You know,
we made these קל וחומרים, kal v'chomerim, right?
So, and but we only stopped at a certain point. We didn’t
say it goes on forever. We stopped by רביעי revi'i, בקודש, ba-kodesh
right? And the point being though, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who has
everything one level down in חולין chullin didn’t say anything further in
terms of a further level than what we already knew in תרומה
and קדשים, kodoshim, right? So, are we trying to say that in
the, you know, like, "Oh, well, is absence of evidence evidence?" Or
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn’t say it, okay fine, so what? Who
knows he doesn’t hold it? So the point being then we had
another teaching that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had that only got you
up until רביעי revi'i, בקודש. That’s the point. We do have an
explicit teaching that gets you up to רביעי בקודש. And if we
were dealing with קל וחומרים, kal v'chomerim, we should have gone further.
That’s basically the way I’m trying to explain this here. Does that
make, you know, there’s this whole long רש"י about these different קל
וחומרים kal v'chomerim which I’m trying to spare everybody.
But that’s basically the point.
We have this כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו kli m'tzaref mah she-b'tocho, and
it’s not because, you know, it’s not because one touches the other
touches the other touches the other because אין לדבר סוף. ein l'davar
sof. It’s because the כלי, the
utensil, is if you will combining it all and you only get
as far as a רביעי, not further. That’s the point. Okay. אמר
קסבר צירוף דרבנן ופליגי
דרבי חנין. Amar kasavar tziruf
d'Rabbanan u-pligi d'Rabbi Chanin.
So he holds that this צירוף tziruf is דרבנן d'Rabbanan and
that
the כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו, kli m'tzaref mah she-b'tocho. the כלי combines
everything in there.
So the point is, why do we see it’s, what do you
mean צירוף דרבנן? tziruf d'Rabbanan? How do I know it’s דרבנן? d'Rabbanan?
Because the point is that
all our cases in the תורה Torah was אוכלין or משקין, mashkin
foodstuff, right? We,
you know, then כלים keilim also, but we rejected that. We said
that
there’s no טומאת כלים מן התורה. tum'at keilim min ha-Torah. So but
רבי עקיבא’s Rabbi Akiva saying even in... So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is holding this צירוף tzeruf concept is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, and then פליגא
pliga דרבי חנין, d'Rabbi Chanin, he and he disagrees with רבי חנין
Rabbi Chanin דאמר צירוף דאורייתא, damar tzeruf d'oraisa, because שנאמר shenemar with
the קורבנות korbanot of the נשיאים, nesi'im, כף אחת עשרה זהב מלאה
קטורת. kaf achas asara zahav meleia ketores.
So when they when they brought this they brought a כף, kaf,
like a ladle, yeah,
that it weighed or was had a value of of ten שקלים
shkalim and was full of קטורת. So it says כף אחת, kaf
achas, הכתוב עשה את כל מה שבכף אחת. hakatuv asa es kol
ma shebakaf achas. It says כף אחת kaf achas although it means
one cup, they brought one one ladle as opposed to two, but
the point being we're דרשנין dorshnin it to say the כף kaf
makes everything אחת, achas, it makes it all one. So he says
anyway this point being this צירוף tzeruf he learns this from a
פסוק. So he's saying מדאורייתא mideraisa it would be. But רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says it's דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
Okay, fine.
So I'll let you at least feel better about something here. We're
done with this טומאת משקין tumas mashkin for the
at least for the time being. I mean we're generally done with
it. We're not done with טומאה though.
So
the we had a whole bunch of opinions over here, just remember
like I'm not going to get into what they all were but
there's רבי עקיבא Akiva and there's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, right? You
know how far do you take these things? And then you have
רבי עקיבא's saying you know remember רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi explaining רבי
עקיבא's opinion would be but he doesn't hold like him. So so
again you have רבי עקיבא's opinion, רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi opinion, you
also have רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right? You know which which was
the the most מיקל meikel on this and then you have רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who was the more מחמיר machmir but then he
may have reversed his opinion and then yeah and then and then
you know then we had רב אלעזר Rav Elazar which was the
more you know who is potentially somewhere in the middle. So רב
אלעזר, Rav Elazar, yeah. So those were all our opinions.
Okay so now we're going to go onto a a different topic
of תנן התם: tenan hasam: המחט שנמצאת בבשר. hamachat shenimtzes babasar.
So now we're talk now no more משקין, this is a separate
case. So you know the question is
how far are we going to take this.
And the reason we're talking about this because you know how far
how far do you extend טומאה? Right before we're talking about you
know do you extend משקין what levels how many levels down. So
now we're going to have a similar case, המחט שנמצאת בבשר, שהסכין
והידיים טהורות hamachat shenimtzes babasar shehasakin vehayadayim tehoros. והבשר טמא. נמצאת בפרש
הכל טהור. nimtzes beferesh hakol tahor.
So now let's say you have this this needle. A needle is
a metal object. So you have a needle, you שחט shachted your
animal of קדשים, right? And this and the reason also this is
brought here is because this רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, Rabbi Chanina Segan
HaKohanim, right? He said this whole thing about you know and we
talked about חמץ chametz and תרומה טהורה, terumah tehorah, right? So he's
saying something else here now. So he's saying that this you שחט
shachted this animal and you found this needle in it, right? And
we're going to explain why this needle's presumed to be טמא, but
take it for the moment that this this needle is טמא. Okay
fine. So now the meat of of this קורבן korban is now
טמא. But what about the hands of the כהנים kohanim that did
the שחיטה? shechitah? What about the knife itself? Are those טמא? Do
we assume that like his hands touched the area where the needle
is? Do we assume the knife, you know let's say he was
cutting the meat or something like that.
Do we assume that the knife when cutting the meat touched the
needle? Right? So that's the case. המחט שנמצאת בבשר hamachat shenimtzes babasar,
שהסכין והידיים ve-ha-yadayim טהורות. tehoros No, we don't assume that the that
the knife touched the needle or that his hands touched the needle.
However, בשר טמא. basar tamei. נמצאת בפרש הכל טהור. nimtzes beferesh hakol
tahor. If if it was found in the excrement of this animal
everything is טהור tahor. including the including the בשר. basar. So אמר
רבי עקיבא זכינו שאין טומאת ידיים במקדש.
amar Rabbi Akiva zachinu she'ein
tumas yadayim baMikdash.
So we've come out ahead. We're fortunate. It's a זכות zechus for
us that that that there's no טומאת ידיים tumas yadayim in the
מקדש Mikdash over here because again
if you think it's not more lenient in the מקדש Mikdash just
think you know he says we've come out ahead. It's that we're
more מחמיר machmir everywhere else. You know what I mean? Because this
whole טומאת ידיים tumas yadayim really is more of a דרבנן d'rabbanan
thing and you know it's just a way of looking at orienting
ourselves with that. It so they didn't impose that in the מקדש.
Mikdash. They imposed it outside because if there you know if סתם
ידיים stam yadayim are טמאות temeios outside of the מקדש Mikdash which
they are, then why would you say ידיים yadayim are טהורות over
here? So the point being that we didn't actually have a גזירה
gezeira of טומאת ידיים tumas yadayim in the מקדש, Mikdash, right?
Okay, so now the question is though if you if you were
paying attention that
the
case was המחט הסכין והידיים טהורות. hamachat hasakin vehayadayim tehoros. So
ונאמר שאין טומאת ידיים וכלים במקדש, v'neimar she-ein tumat yadayim v'keilim b'mikdash,
right? So don't say that there's also no טומאת כלים tumas keilim
in the מקדש Mikdash because because why do you leave that out?
Right? Because he said that the case was a סכין, sakin, which
is a כלי, and the ruling was that it's טהור. עקיבא just
talked about ידיים. yadayim. So why didn't he say that?
So so our answer
is
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, it's it's
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, ידיים קודם גזירת
כלים נשנו. yadayim kodem gezeiras keilim nishnu. The reason we didn't do
that was because it was timing
because we already had an old
תקנה takanah מדרבנן mi-drabbanan about טומאת ידיים tumas yadayim and there was
no טומאת כלים tumas keilim במקדש, Hamikdash, right? So the point is
we
didn't... or anywhere for that matter.
So you wouldn't have to say that we came out ahead that
there's no טומאת כלים tumas keilim במקדש Hamikdash because there was no
טומאת כלים tumas keilim at all at that point, right?
So that's why he didn't need to say it.
But then there's two גזירות gezeirot and he's making his comment
after the גזירה gezeirah on
ידיים yadayim but before
the גזירה gezeirah on כלים. keilim. So you didn't need to mention
anything because there's nothing to mention. So
but
we're going to... we're going to chuck that answer in a second.
אמר רבא הא דתרוייהו באותו יום גזרו. Amar Rava ha d'tarvaihu b'oto
yom gazru.
What do you mean it was before the כלים? keilim?
ידיים yadayim and כלים keilim came at the same time and there
were these famous eighteen things that you know that there was a
whole fight between בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and then you know בית שמאי Beis Shammai won the
day in the עליה aliyah was in somebody's house, חנניה
בן חזקיה בן גרון.
Chananya
ben Chizkiya ben Garon.
Yeah, good memory.
So anyway, all that was at the same day, דתנן, in that
day, הספר, ha-sefer, ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh actually are מטמא, metamei, they
made that גזירה, gezeirah, והידיים
which is one, והטבול יום, ve-ha-tevul yom, והאוכלים והכלים, ve-ha-ochlin ve-ha-keilim, right?
So כלים keilim is mentioned at the same time ידיים, yadayim, all
at the same time שניטמאו במשקין, shenitme'u b'mashkin, right? And whatever whatever
whatever. But the point being
that we see clearly ידיים yadayim and כלים keilim are all in
the same sentence. They're all in the same part time. So what
do you mean you're saying it's after one but before the other?
No, they were both at the same time. Okay, so we can't
say that. So now we're back to our question: why didn't רבי
עקיבא mention טומאת כלים tumas keilim is not in the המקדש? Hamikdash?
Since it was around the same time as ידיים yadayim and you
mentioned ידיים, yadayim, why didn't you mention כלים? keilim? אלא אמר רבא
הנח לטומאת סכין דאפילו בחולין נמי לא מטמא. Ela amar Rava hanach
l'tumas sakin d'afilu b'chullin nami lo metamei. So no, because
that we don't have to say it because because even in...
it shouldn't be טמא at all, even in חולין. chullin. Why not?
היי סכין דנגע במאי? Hai sakin d'naga b'mai? What are we worried
about? What could it have possibly touched to become טמא that now
you're saying we're very lucky we don't have this גזירה gezeirah in
the המקדש Hamikdash about טומאת כלים? tumas keilim? It wouldn't have been
טמא anyway because why? אילימא דנגע בבשר? Ilima d'naga b'vasar? הא אין
אוכל מטמא כלי. Ha ein ochel metamei kli.
So we know, we mentioned this whole thing about
that אוכל ochel not מטמא כלי, metamei kli, right? That was that
whole thing that we had before about יטמא יטמא and we said
it can only you know אוכל ochel to משקין and משקין to
אוכל ochel but אוכל ochel can't be מטמא כלי. metamei kli.
Okay, so it hit the needle, it hit the needle.
Ah, okay, ואלא דנגע במחט, v'ela d'naga b'machat, right? That's the next
line. Okay, fine. So it didn't touch... so it's not because it
touched the food because that wouldn't work.
But הא אין כלי מטמא כלי. ha ein kli metamei kli. But
the מחט machat itself is a כלי and the סכין sakin is
a כלי. So a כלי can't be מטמא metamei a כלי. Remember?
Like also sort of like... like won't be מטמא metamei like.
Wait wait wait I just want to make sure I understand that.
Let's say you have a small
cup inside a big cup.
Okay. And you put a dead שרץ inside the small cup. Right?
The big cup and you have food inside the big cup on
the outside of but not touching the small cup.
Well this is a little bit different because remember you know we
have two concepts here. One is also כלי חרס, kli cheres, you
know it's מטמא מאוירו, metamei mei-aviro, so it's a little bit different.
So the air is טמא and then you know if it's a
כלי חרס. kli cheres. Now the other thing would also be we
had this teaching of כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו.
So you know those... that may be a little bit different. I
don't want to necessarily apply your case over there. But this is
a case of just touching another not combined with anything else.
Okay that was clarifying. In other words just thinking about just one
piece of metal touching another piece of metal. Right.
Metal object that's a כלי.
Right but metal's different also and we're going to get to that.
But I assume these are metal.
Yes.
סכין Sakin is metal and the מחט machat is metal.
But that could be part of the whole reason that metal's different.
But the point is though at this point we're saying so why
would it become טמא *Tamei* if it's because it touched the meat
that certainly that wouldn't work? And even if it touched the מחט
*Machat* it wouldn't work it wouldn't become טמא *Tamei* because אין כלי
מטמא כלי *Ein Kli Metamei Kli*.
Right. So even חולין *Chulin* it wouldn't have been a problem. So
that's why you didn't need to say that we gained in the
מקדש *Mikdash* because it wouldn't have been a problem anyway. So okay
so now getting back to this teaching and I want to get
this a little bit further. האי מחט מאי עבידתיה *Hai Machat Mai
Avidteih*? Remember our whole point was this needle is in the is
in the meat, the meat is טמא *Tamei* but nothing else essentially,
right? The ידיים *Yadayim* are not טמא *Tamei*, the סכין *Sakin* are
not טמא *Tamei*, but our question is why is the meat טמא
*Tamei* to begin with? We're assuming obviously that this מחט *Machat* is
טמא *Tamei*. But why? האי מחט מאי עבידתיה *Hai Machat Mai Avidteih*?
What did this come from? In other words why what's it doing
here? How'd it become to make things טמא *Tamei*? נימא ספק safek,
מחט *Nema Safek Machat* that for we're saying okay we're just assuming
for whatever reason needles are טמא
*Tamei* מספק *MiSafek*. והתניא רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי ורבי חנינא לא גזרו
על ספק safek הרוקין שבירושלים *VeAtanya Rabbi Elazar VeRabbi Yosei VeRabbi Chanina
Lo Gazru Al Safek HaRukin SheBiYerushalayim*. בחד אמר לא גזרו על ספק
safek הכלים שבירושלים
*BeChad Amar Lo Gazru Al Safek HaKeilim SheBiYerushalayim*. Now remember there's
פסוקים *Psukim* in the תורה *Torah* that וכי ירוק הזב *VeChi Yarok
HaZav*, right? Let's say there's a זב *Zav* was טמא *Tamei*. Spits,
right? Then his spit can make you טמא *Tamei*, right? So okay.
So now let's say
there's I'm walking on the street and there's spit on the ground.
I'm in ירושלים yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, right? And or I'm some place else
and we'll see the difference between where I am.
And there's spit there.
So do I assume that this spit is from a זב *Zav*,
right? If the spit is from a זב *Zav* I'm טמא *Tamei*.
If the spit is not from a זב *Zav* then I'm טהור
*Tahor*. So I didn't see anyone spit, but there's spit on the
ground. So let's say someone touched it. So it's a ספק safek.
*Safek*. So one says לא גזרו על ספק רוקין שבירושלים *Lo Gazru
Al Safek Rukin SheBiYerushalayim*. So we're not so מספק *MiSafek* we're not
going to say in ירושלים yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* that you're טמא *Tamei*. Elsewhere
because since it's ירושלים yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and ירושלים yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*
is an area it would be
more difficult to introduce טומאה *Tumah*. Right. Or you could say that
מסתמא *Mistama* most people are טהור *Tahor* because ירושלים yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* has
an elevated level because קדשים *Kodashim* you can eat all sorts of
things there you can't eat outside. People want to keep themselves in
a state of טהרה *Taharah*. So we assume that most the זבים
*Zavim* would be more careful about spitting in public and that's the
highest טהרה *Taharah*. פשיטא דפשיטא
*Pshita DePshita*. Okay. So anyway one said that we're not going to
say מספק *MiSafek* the רוק *Rok* is טמא *Tamei* in ירושלים yerushalayim.
*Yerushalayim*. וחד אמר לא גזרו על ספק כלים שבירושלים *VeChad Amar Lo
Gazru Al Safek Keilim SheBiYerushalayim*, right? So ספק כלים בירושלים *Safek Keilim
BiYerushalayim* also will not be טמא *Tamei* because presumably people don't want
to be leaving טמא *Tamei* utensils in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Anyway the point
being then if at most it's a ספק *Safek*, this כלי *Kli*.
That's what we're saying at this point. And this כלי *Kli* is
in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. If this כלי *Kli* is in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* it
should be טהור *Tahor*, right? לא גזרו על ספק כלים שבירושלים *Lo
Gazru Al Safek Keilim SheBiYerushalayim*. We just said that. So why are
we saying that this מחט *Machat* which is a כלי *Kli* that's
in the animal you slaughtered is now טמא *Tamei*? Why? At most
it should be a ספק *Safek* and a ספק *Safek* should be
טהור *Tahor*.
What is the assumption is you could never really know the circumstances
under which there was a needle that you found stuck inside the
flesh of a
cow or a קרבן *Korban*. Right.
How in the world could it be it has to have an
element of ספק *Safek*.
Right. So now our question is why are we saying it's טמא
*Tamei*? That's our question. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הכא לאו בספק
*Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Hacha Lav BeSafek* כגון שאבד לו מחט
טמא מת *Kegon SheIvad Lo Machat Temei Met* והכירה בבשר *VeHikirah BaBasar*.
It's not a case of ספק *Safek*. It's a case of ודאי
*Vadai*. I well or more
or less ספק *Safek*.
So the point being that I know a טמא מת *Temei Met*
touched this מחט *Machat* this needle. And guess what? Here it is.
That's that needle. So that's why the בשר *Basar* is טמא *Tamei*.
That makes sense.
And it refers to the guy himself the טמא מת
*Temei Met*.
A טמא מת *Temei Met* touched the needle, right? So the needle's
now טמא *Tamei* and this needle can now make the בשר *Basar*
טמא *Tamei*.
Right. So it's guy who's a טמא מת *Temei Met* and he
lost a needle. The tailor was a טמא מת *Temei Met*.
And guess what?
Hey where's my needle? I found it in the פה *Pei* of
the sheep.
Yes.
The animal that was about to be slaughtered.
Oh there's my needle.
Where's my needle?
That's our case. So wild.
And the needles are very valuable and expensive.
Okay.
So that's basically your answer is אינה הכי נמי *Ina Hachi Nami*.
It's not a case of ספק *Safek*. It's a case of ודאי
*Vadai*, right? That's essentially our answer. And we constructed a case obviously
a case of ודאי *Vadai* whether or not you consider it likely
that's not the point. The point is you're right מספק *MiSafek* it
shouldn't be a problem. Therefore it's not a ספק *Safek*.
והכירה בבשר *VeHikirah BaBasar*.
רבי יוסי
בר אבין *Rabbi Yosei Bar Abin*. אמר כגון שהייתה פרה חסומה ובאה
מחוץ לירושלים. kegon shehayta para chasuma uvah michutz liyerushalayim. I know, it
could still be a case of ספק, but we said oh we
don't גוזר gozer ספק in ירושלים. Okay, this is a case, I'll
explain. This is a case where, where the cow came outside from
ירושלים and it was muzzled, so we know it couldn't, so we
know it couldn't have swallowed anything in ירושלים because, you know, it
had to come from outside. So this needle had to come from
outside. And from outside we did say, we do say ספק is
טמא, not טהור.
So it is a case of ספק.
So either the cow lived in Jerusalem, but the טומאה it made,
the טמא it made, was, or the cow lived outside of Jerusalem.
And the needle came from outside of ירושלים into ירושלים, presumably, because
it was muzzled, and it wouldn't, it didn't, you know, ingest anything
while it was in ירושלים.
Right? I mean, because you brought it, let's say, right there, you
know, it came from right outside and you brought it right to
the בית המקדש that day, so it didn't have a chance to
eat.
So presumably this needle came from outside.
By the way, I mean, another way it's clear, right, the way
that the needle got in is the cow ate the needle, so
that's believable too. Right.
Right. All right, so the question is do we stop now? It's
already 8:31. Okay.
Thank you.
Wow, that was solid work.